Downing Cless Papers MS218
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Downing Cless Papers
1962 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Cless, Downing
MS218
3.6 Linear Feet 3 boxes
26 Sheets
This collections contains the papers of Downing Cless, professor in the Department of Drama.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Downing Cless, 2014-2019.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series: Course materials, correspondence and publications; Productions; and 2017 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
Downing Cless joined the Department of Drama at Tufts University in 1979. Downing began as a junior faculty member, then became an associate professor three years later. He later became Professor of Drama, and served as department chair for two terms, for six years and again for three. Downing retired in May 2014.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains files and set drawings on productions directed by or involving Downing Cless. This collection also contains course and curriculum material related to Stage Left and TheaterWorks. Materials include correspondence, research materials, writings, scripts, programs, director's notes, and photographs.
Faculty papers; Teaching and learning; Drama; Cless, Downing
- Course materials, correspondence, and publications, 1962 -- 2014; MS218.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains course and curriculum materials, correspondence, notes, departmental business, files related to Stage Left and TheaterWorks, and research and writings materials.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in its original order, as created by Downing Cless.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Resolution on the Retirement of Downing Cless, 2014; MS218.001.001.00001 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Curriculum, Theatre, 1972 -- 1998; MS218.001.001.00002 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Department Business, 1991 -- 1999; MS218.001.001.00003 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - TELI, 1990 - 1992, MS218.001.001.00004 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Stage Left Business, 1981 -- 1984; MS218.001.001.00005 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - TheaterWorks Business, 1985 -- 1989; MS218.001.001.00006 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Pacific Events, Inc., 1970 -- 1971; MS218.001.001.00007 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979 -- 2004; MS218.001.001.00008 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Senior Thesis, 1966; MS218.001.001.00009 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Papers, Sociology, 1964 -- 1968; MS218.001.001.00010 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Sociological Theory, 1963 -- 1972; MS218.001.001.00011 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Dissertation, 1978; MS218.001.001.00012 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Charisma Paper, 1967 -- 1969; MS218.001.001.00013 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Papers, Drama, 1962 -- 2011; MS218.001.001.00014 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Metacommunication Article, 1981; MS218.001.001.00015 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Irony Study, 1979; MS218.001.001.00016 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Irony, 1963 -- 1981; MS218.001.001.00017 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Williams and Brecht Study, 1980 -- 1982; MS218.001.001.00018 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Eco-Theatre Research and Writings, 1995 -- 2012; MS218.001.001.00019 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Notes on Theater, 1966 - 1973, 1966 -- 1985; MS218.001.001.00020 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Course file for Drama 155: Directing I, circa 2013; MS218.001.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_6d30b4f68e6f95ace67df7784324d3f4, Folder 1, Box 2)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Downing Cless, 2016, accession MS-2017-019.
    This folder includes syllabus, assignments, and notes.
  - "Oedipus the King and Antigone" script, circa 2011 -- 2013; MS218.001.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_6d30b4f68e6f95ace67df7784324d3f4, Folder 2, Box 2)
  - Course file for Drama 156: Directing II, circa 1980 -- 2013; MS218.001.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_6d30b4f68e6f95ace67df7784324d3f4, Folder 3, Box 2)
    Gift of Downing Cless, 2019, accession MS-2019-072.
  - ASTR and CDC Papers, circa 2010 -- 2014; MS218.001.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_6d30b4f68e6f95ace67df7784324d3f4, Folder 4, Box 2)
    This file contains a project plan for Cless's research leave 2013-2014, research material, a paper presented at the American Society for Theater Research conference (2010), and a CDC paper. Topics include climater change and theater.
  - SILA, circa 2012 -- 2014; MS218.001.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_6d30b4f68e6f95ace67df7784324d3f4, Folder 5, Box 2)
    This file contains programs, notes, and correspondence relating to SILA, presented by the Underground Railway Theater at Central Square Theater in 2014.
- Productions, 1963 -- 2011; MS218.002; 3.6 Linear Feet
  This series contains files on individual productions directed by Downing Cless,1969-2011. Files typically contain scripts, programs, director's notes, correspondence, news clippings, and photographs.
  This series is arranged chronologically, with a few exceptions, as arranged by Downing Cless.
  - Deathwatch, 1969; MS218.002.001.00021 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Caligula, 1969; MS218.002.001.00022 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Baal, 1970; MS218.002.001.00023 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Night of the Iguana, 1970; MS218.002.001.00024 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - The Empire Builders, 1973; MS218.002.001.00025 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Tom Paine, 1973; MS218.002.001.00026 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Sports Play, 1973 -- 1975; MS218.002.001.00027 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Streetcar, 1974; MS218.002.001.00028 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - The Kitchen, 1974; MS218.002.001.00029 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - The Drunkard, 1974; MS218.002.001.00030 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - The Tempest, 1975; MS218.002.001.00031 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Hearst, 1976; MS218.002.001.00032 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Merry Wives of Windsor, 1976; MS218.002.001.00033 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - You Can't Take it with You, 1977; MS218.002.001.00034 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Three Sisters, 1978; MS218.002.001.00035 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Employees Only, 1977 -- 1978; MS218.002.001.00036 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Come and Go, 1979; MS218.002.001.00037 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Major Barbara, 1980; MS218.002.001.00038 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Barbara, Prompt Script, 1980; MS218.002.001.00039 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Shelter Skelter, 1979 -- 1981; MS218.002.001.00040 (Box MS218 Shared 1)
  - Imaginary Invalid, 1980; MS218.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Camino Real, 1980; MS218.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Camino Text, 1980; MS218.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Loot, 1981; MS218.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Ladyhouse Blues, 1981; MS218.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Too True to be Good, 1982; MS218.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Puntila, 1982; MS218.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - The Physicists, 1983; MS218.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - How I Got That Story, 1982 -- 1983; MS218.002.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - We Won't Pay, 1983; MS218.002.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Lower Depths, Notes etc, 1984; MS218.002.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Lower Depths, Script, 1984; MS218.002.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - The Year Boston Won the Pennant, 1984; MS218.002.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Factwino, 1985; MS218.002.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - The Nation Thief, 1985; MS218.002.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - The Island, 1986; MS218.002.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Sanctuary: Harriet Tubman, 1986 -- 1988; MS218.002.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - Lysistrata, 1986; MS218.002.002.00018 (Box 2)
  - Lysistrata, Script, 1986; MS218.002.002.00019 (Box 2)
  - Mensch Meier, 1987; MS218.002.002.00020 (Box 2)
  - White House Murder Case, 1987; MS218.002.002.00021 (Box 2)
  - Accidental Death of an Anarchist, 1988; MS218.002.002.00022 (Box 2)
  - Dinosaurs, 1988 -- 1989; MS218.002.002.00023 (Box 2)
  - Marat Sade, 1989; MS218.002.002.00024 (Box 2)
  - Midsummer, 1991; MS218.002.002.00025 (Box 2)
  - Christopher Columbus Follies, 1992; MS218.002.002.00026 (Box 2)
  - The Birds, 1992; MS218.002.002.00027 (Box 2)
  - Threepenny Opera, 1979 -- 1993; MS218.002.002.00028 (Box 2)
  - Threepenny, Director's Text, 1993; MS218.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Kentucky Cycle, 1994 -- 1995; MS218.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Kentucky Cycle Script, 1994; MS218.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Intoxicating, 1994 -- 2003; MS218.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Alice in Wonderland, 1996 -- 1997; MS218.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Skin of our Teeth, 2000; MS218.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Doctor Faustus, 2003; MS218.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Rain. Some Fish. No Elephants., 2007; MS218.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Madwoman of Caillot, 2008; MS218.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Madwoman, Script, 2008; MS218.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Oedipus and Antigone, 2011; MS218.002.003.00011; 2 Folder(s) (Box 3, Box data_value_missing_6d30b4f68e6f95ace67df7784324d3f4, Folder 2)
  - Waiting for Godot, 1982; MS218.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - The Kitchen, Television, 1979; MS218.002.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Star Wars (SDI), 1983; MS218.002.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - Bombios, 1985 -- 1988; MS218.002.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Computer Project, 1983; MS218.002.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Nightingale, URT, 1990; MS218.002.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Sold Out, 1987; MS218.002.003.00018 (Box 3)
  - History-Lit Courses, 1963 -- 1978; MS218.002.003.00019 (Box 3)
  - Scene Study, 1979 -- 1986; MS218.002.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - DR 112, Political Acting, 2005; MS218.002.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - DR 01, Day to Day Tragedy, 1969 -- 2004; MS218.002.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - DR 01, Comedy, 1986 -- 1999; MS218.002.003.00023 (Box 3)
  - DR 01 Exams, 2004 -- 2009; MS218.002.003.00024 (Box 3)
  - Sociology of Theater, 1970 -- 2011; MS218.002.003.00025 (Box 3)
  - Seminar, Eco-Theatre, 1998 -- 2010; MS218.002.003.00026 (Box 3)
  - DR 10, Environment, 1990 -- 1999; MS218.002.003.00027 (Box 3)
  - Ecology Americas, 1991 -- 1996; MS218.002.003.00028 (Box 3)
  - Unlabelled Slides from Student Production, MS218.002.003.00029 (Box 3)
- 2017 accessions, 1978 -- 1981; MS218.003; 26 Sheets
  This series is arranged in received order.
  This series is open for research.
  Transferred by Downing Cless, 2017, accession MS-2018-013.
  This series contains hand-drawn set and lighting designs for the following productions: Lion in Winter, 1980; Jest!, 1979; Loot, 1981; Major Barbara, 1980; The Knight of the Burning Pestle, 1978; R, 1978; Summit Conference, 1981; Toys in the Attic, 1981; Diary of Anne Frank, 1978; Cat on a Hot Tin Roof, 1979; Camino Real, 1980; A Fable, 1978; The Ghost Sonata, 1978; The Haunted House, 1979.
  - Set and lighting designs, 1978 -- 1981; MS218.003.001; 26 Sheets (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 9)
    This file contains hand-drawn set and lighting designs for the following productions: Lion in Winter, 1980; Jest!, 1979; Loot, 1981; Major Barbara, 1980; The Knight of the Burning Pestle, 1978; R, 1978; Summit Conference, 1981; Toys in the Attic, 1981; Diary of Anne Frank, 1978; Cat on a Hot Tin Roof, 1979; Camino Real, 1980; A Fable, 1978; The Ghost Sonata, 1978; The Haunted House, 1979.